Guide to the International Monitor Institute. Middle East videotapes, 1991-2008 RL.00606
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Middle East videotapes, circa 1991-2008, 80 boxes
  - Operation Provide Comfort-Tape 4, NTSC Beta [TRT:0:58:40] (1 copy; 1 original) (Box 417, Video-cassette ME058)
    Tape 4 Shows Kurdish refugee camp Yekmal; refugees loading possessions into trucks and climbing in (leaving to return to Iran); interview with Maj Rick Helfer (USA) explaining responsibilities and situation at this camp; and Combat Control Team (CCT) activity. Includes troop re-deployment, troops loading baggage onto pallets and forklift loading pallets onto C-130E and troops boarding; reenlistment ceremony in front of Saddam Hussein`s summer palace at Sarseng, Iraq; then 36th CES posing for pictures. Also shows Psychological Operations personnel patrolling through small towns in HMMWV interacting with children and giving maps of food distribution points to men, AAVS photographer and British Commandos in some scenes; and church food distribution point.
  - Operation Provide Comfort-Tape 14, NTSC Beta [TRT:0:26:18] (Box 323, Video-cassette ME068)
    Original Credits: From Defense Visual Information Center at March Air Force Base (DIVAC)
    Covers humanitarian relief given to Kurdish refugees by US Joint Services Task Force and Coalition forces. Shows Kurdish camps and towns in the mountains along the Iraqi - Turkish border with Joint Task Forces (JTF) organizing camps, distributing food; giving medical care; and patrolling area to protect Kurds from Iraqi soldiers. Coverage of US and coalition forces assistance to Kurdish refugees who fled to the mountains along the Iraqi-Turkish border. Note: Tapes 1 through 10 contains 553:23 unedited documentation and Tapes 11 through 14 contains 198:55 edited clips.
    Tape 14 shows clips show medical care for babies; convoy; JTF personnel celebrate 4th of July with raft race on Tigris river, barbecue and fireworks; loading of heavy equipment aboard the "Meroandia Tradu II" at Iskenderun; Psychological Operations personnel working with Kurdish children; Prime Beef team at Silopi; General Colin Powell at briefing. Also shows interviews with personnel describing their mission and experiences, including UN Representative John Tillman.
  - Operation Provide Comfort-Tape 17, NTSC Beta [TRT:0:51:48] (Box 323, Video-cassette ME069)
    Tape 17 shows Seabees unloading equipment with forklift in Zakhu, Iraq on 1991 Apr. 29. Interviews with individual Seabees; troops with field packs walking through field; USMC CH-46Es onloading pallets of cartons of bottles water and supplies then lifting off; AVs of base, tent city, city, river, road, mountains, palace; Kurdish refugee camps in mountains of Northern Iraq and Turkey on 1991 May 1; Joint Task Force groups meeting; USA medics giving measles inoculations to children; and interview with Sergeant Avery (USA) medical coordinator.
  - 60 Minutes: Halabja: Ten Years After [1998 Mar. 1], NTSC Beta [TRT:0:13:13] (Box 356: 1 copy; Box 417: 1 original) (Box 356 and 417, Video-cassette ME072)
    Producer: 60 Minutes CBS
    Original Credits: Reporter: Ed Bradley. Producer: Jeanne Solomon Langley
    Ed Bradley interview with Dr. Christine Gosdin who travelled to Halabja, Iraq with a British camera crew (see tape 016) ten years after the poison gas attack on Halabja by Saddam Hussein to measure long term effects of poison gas on population. Footage of the aftermath of the attack on the town and the scant attention paid to the situation in Iraq, and the effects of chemical weapons on humans. Footage of the town and the little building that has gone on since the attack in 1988 Mar., little or no reconstruction has gone on since then. She discusses the details of what chemicals Saddam used in his attacks. Footage also includes the effects on the nerves of the civilian population ten years later and the pleas by the local population.
  - Iran Behind the Veil, NTSC VHS [TRT:0:50:00] (Box 348: 1 copy; Box 411: 1 original) (Box 348 and 411, Video-cassette ME075)
    Producer: Unknown Producer. No Credits?
    Original Credits: Reporter and Host: Mary Alice Williams
    Network TV (provenance unknown) documentary about the Islamic revolution in Iran, a lot of raw footage, of Khomeini, Mansour Farhang, former Ambassador to the UN, the inner workings of Khomeini's theocracy, history of Iran, the Shah and the revolution, Daniel Pipes interview.
  - The Mock War Crimes Trial of Saddam Hussein (Vol. 1), NTSC VHS [TRT:1:59:00] (1 original) (Box 411, Video-cassette ME076)
    Producer: American Bar Association: Section of International Law and Practice
    Original Credits: News Footage Courtesy CNN. Edit Facilities Courtesy Troika Productions. Edited for Presentation By Jack Niesi. Came to us from the Documentation Center of Cambodia (DC CAM)
    Mock up of potential war crime trial of Saddam Hussein.
  - Sorrow and Anticipation and a Little Hope, NTSC VHS [TRT:0:28:00] (Box 348: 1 copy; Box 411: 1 original) (Box 348 and 411, Video-cassette ME077)
    Producer: Produced by the Committee for Humanitarian Assistance to Iranian Refugees (CHAIR), 1996 May
    Original Credits: With English Subtitles. Videotaped and Edited by: Maryam Namazie. Collaborators: Ramesh Ahmadi and Keyvan Javid
    Documentary about the plight of Iranian refugees, fleeing the Islamic Republic, in Turkey. Statements by refugees and their families about the problems of living in Turkey and the unfilled promises of Turks and other international relief organizations, particularly harsh criticism of United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees (UNHCR). Also some history of the plight of Iranian refugees and statements of political prisoners who escaped the Islamic Republic.
  - Outtakes From Michael Wood Documentaries-Tape 1, PAL VHS [TRT:2:30:00] (Box 348: 2 copies; Box 411: 1 original) (Box 348 and 411, Video-cassette ME078)
    Tape on two working copies.
    Outtakes from Michael Wood documentary on the Marsh Arabs in Southern Iraq and the situation under Saddam Hussein after the Gulf War (see ME record 004 for completed documentary), includes interview with an Iraqi political prisoner, outtakes of scenes with Thaer al-Hadairi in Tehran, shots of villages in the marshes of southern Iraq, interviews with Iraqi villagers in Southern Iraq.
    Plus other miscellaneous stuff, Falklands war, human rights stuff.
  - Outtakes From Michael Wood Documentaries- Tape 2, PAL VHS [TRT:3:00:00] (Box 348: 2 copies; Box 411: 1 original) (Box 348 and 411, Video-cassette ME079)
    Outtakes of Michael Wood trip to Southern Iraq, interviews with villagers, scenes of refugee settlements and shots of the marshes in Southern Iraq.
  - Chemical Attack on Halabja, PAL VHS [TRT:0:30:00] (Box 348, Video-cassette ME080)
    Producer: Iranian TV
    Same as ME45
    Raw footage from the aftermath of the gas attack by Saddam's forces on the northern Iraqi town of Halabja. Shot by Iranian news crews, with scenes of the bombed out town and dead civilians with some commentary and interviews of residents in Persian and some English translation.
    Halabja.
  - Marshes of Southern Iraq during the Uprising, PAL VHS [TRT:1:10:00] (Box 348: 1 copy; Box 411: 1 original) (Box 348 and 411, Video-cassette ME081)
    Some dates 1992 Jul.
    Raw footage of unknown provenance taken in the marsh region of southern Iraq during and after the rebellion of the region against Saddam at the end of the Gulf War, in 1992, footage dated 1992 Jul. on camera occasionally, some of the footage of poor quality. Footage with British voice over of shots of Iraqi army positions and refugees during and after the Uprising following the Gulf War. Interviews and translations of rebels, of civilians involved in the uprising. Also includes radio broadcasts of calls for help from people under attack in the marshes by Iraqi attacks. Also includes shots of hospitals and refugees.
    00:02:40 - Footage in Arabic, needs translation; you can hear the voice over of the cameraman in Arabic describing the scene. Includes footage of craters and other burned out villages and settlements and interviews with villagers and women and children along the marshes.
  - Iraq Video, PAL VHS [TRT:1:37:00](Box 348: 3 copies; Box 411: 1 original) (Box 348 and 411, Video-cassette ME082)
    Raw footage of the Arab uprising in southern Iraq after the Gulf war some dates showing 1991 Mar. 10-11 with Arabic voiceover of conflict in Iraq, shots of people fighting in Basra and Najaf, war in the south, the Gulf War, some interviews with Saddam, stock footage of early Iraqi scenes and of Faisal part of some sort of documentary on the history of Iraq and colonialism, and interviews with Iraqi's who claim they were tortured, shots of people hanging in public squares,
  - Marsh Arab Clipreel / Iraq Marshes-A Good Reason for Sanctions? Mar. 1995 -, PAL VHS [TRT:0:34:00] (Box 348: 1 copy; Box 411: 1 original) (Box 348 and 411, Video-cassette ME083)
    Producer: Journeyman Pictures
    Part A-Clipreel
    00:01:00 Baghdad household goods market (more and more Iraqi's sell possessions to survive amid rocketing inflation).
    00:02:11 Basra-children's hospital.
    00:05:17 Interview: Dr. Bashar Jamil.
    00:05:50 Gulf War destruction in Basra.
    00:06:20 Saddam's portrait painter.
    00:07:07 Black and white footage of Iraqis helicopters bombing Kurds in 1988 when chemical attacks against Kurds were widespread.
    00:07:50 Iraqis execute Kurds.
    00:08:04 Norma Johnson, Amnesty International.
    00:08:30 Marsh Arabs, Shiites, in boat in Marshes.
    00:08:50 Dr. Sahib al-Hakim-Iraqi Human Rights Association.
    00:09:12 Royal Air Force (RAF) aerial footage of Saddam's water diversion canals, river siphons and dams on the river Euphrates in order to drain the Southern Iraqi marshes.
    00:14:28 Food being handed out to Marsh Arab refugees.
    00:16:18 Demonstration on Iranian border by Marsh Arabs
    00:16:45 A speech from the spiritual leader of the marsh arabs Ayatollah Hakim.
    00:18:13 Night attack on Iraqi military camp by Marsh Arabs.
    00:19:18 Dead Iraqi soldiers and aftermath of November 1994 Marsh Arab attack on Iraqi military camp.
    00:22:18 Marsh Arabs sing victory songs after attack.
    00:23:14 Refugee camp on Iranian border.
    00:23:56 Boat arrives at refugee camp with new arrivals from inside the marshes.
    00:24:24 Iraqi soldiers beat Marsh arab prisoners.
    00:25:35 Dr. Ahmed Bayati-spokesman for Supreme Council for Islamic Revolution in Iraq (SCIRI) (Iraqi Marsh Arab Fighters).
    Iraq Marshes-A Good Reason for Sanctions? 1995 Mar.
    00:26:20 Short Journeyman documentary using same clips from above, with narration, evidence of Iraqi military campaign against the marsh arabs, collected by Sahib al-Hakim.
    00:28:35 Shots of boy in hospital injured.
    00:30:50 Shots of woman mourning body wrapped in shroud.
    00:31:03 Dried out marsh shots.
    00:32:22 More dried out marshes.
    00:32:43 Shots of executed men.
    Synopses from Journeyman.
    We offer a look into Iraq's Southern Marshes. Living an ancient life style the Marsh Arabs are a unique race. They're fighting for autonomy from Baghdad. Iraqi rulers have historically accepted the isolation of the Marsh Arabs but not Sadaam Hussein. He is determined to bring them into line. Apart from daily bombardments his army has nearly completed a vast engineering project to drain the marshes. It will allow easy access for his forces. Unique British Royal Air force film shows the engineering work to divert the Euphrates river. Recent footage from inside the marshes depicts the increasingly difficult battles they face. On the Iranian border thousands of refugees have fled the attacks and live in makeshift camps. Other strong footage of Iraqi human rights abuses. The rushes footage also includes Iraqi soldiers ill-treating Marsh Arab prisoners, life inside the Marshes and refugee camps, a children's hospital in Baghdad, Iraqi citizens selling their household goods in Baghdad as they try to survive under the sanctions and footage from Basra - the nearest Iraqi controlled city to the Marshes. Interviews with Marsh Arab organizations and European representatives of Marsh Arab rebels.
  - Iraq-The Fall of Duhok, PAL VHS [TRT:0:14:53] (Box 348: 1 copy; Box 411: 1 original) (Box 348 and 411, Video-cassette ME084)
    Working copy on same tape as ME083 and ME085.
    Working copy starts at 00:36:56.
    The Kurdish people of the city of Dohuk have seen little peace. This feature records their desperate hunt for shelter from the merciless Iraqi regime after the failure of the 1991 Kurdish rebellion. After the Gulf War, when Saddam Hussein's regime was at it's lowest ebb, the Kurdish people rose up. The war-weary Iraqis simply packed their bags and left and the jubilant Kurds destroyed all signs of the regime. They produce macabre Iraqi security Police documents ordering the elimination of 95 percent of 'unfriendly' demonstrators with the other five percent to be interrogated. Iraqi retaliation came swiftly. They shelled Dahok and soon hospital wards were full of bloodied faces of children caught by shrapnel. The city's people fled into the mountains leaving everything they owned, as Iraqi helicopters, which US president George Bush promised would never attack, swooped down. The Kurds were stopped from crossing into Turkey and were forced to march 60km to a remote mountain pass where they camped, waiting for a change in their tragic fortunes.
  - A New Kurdish Crisis (Iraqi, Turkish, Iranian Kurds), PAL VHS [TRT:0:25:00] (Box 348, Video-cassette ME085)
    Working copy on same tape as ME083 and ME084.
    Working copy starts at 00:50:37.
    A new Kurdish war. Ferocious battles have broken out between Turkish and Iraqi Kurds. Iraqi Kurds, in cooperation with the Turks, have taken up arms against their Kurdish brethren, the Kurdistan Workers' Party (PKK) guerilla army. Now the PKK guerrillas, about 10,000 of them, are caught between the Turks and Iraq's Kurdish Peshmerga fighters.
    When Iraq's Kurds won their freedom from Saddam Hussein their victory inspired Turkey and Iran's 12 million Kurds to fight harder than ever for their own freedom. This summer the PKK caused havoc in South East Turkey, plunging vast areas into all out war. The PKK have been using Northern Iraq to train and camp their fighters, helping them vastly with the logistics of their war.
    Now Turkey, by threatening to close their border with Iraq, has forced the Peshmerga to join in battle against the PKK guerrillas. The PKK in turn have also threatened to close all routes into Iraq, asking the humanitarian relief which Iraqi Kurds need to get through the winter. Tension in Southern Turkey is at an all time high with daily battles, towns on strike, and resentment bubbling. This feature covers the mountain battles, the position of the Iraqi Kurds and the tension in Southeast Asia.
    Iranian Kurdish Democratic Party fighting in Iraq and hiding fleeing Iranian shelling, film of infiltrators into the Kurdistan Democratic Party (KDP) of Iran, caught by the Kurds and some confessions.
  - Tides of War, PAL VHS [TRT:0:52:00] (Box 348: 2 copies; Box 411: 1 original) (Box 348 and 411, Video-cassette ME086)
    Producer: Michael McKinnon
    Original Credits: McKinnon Films Production for the National Geographical Society. Produced and Directed by Michael McKinnon. Narrated by Richard Kiley
    "Tides of War" presents the rich and varied marine life of the Gulf, the delicate beauty of the desert and with the outbreak of war, follows the escalating catastrophe from the first oil slick to the capping of the last burning oil well.
  - Frontline: The Survival of Saddam [2000 Jan. 25], NTSC VHS [TRT:0:55:00] (Box 348: 1 copy; Box 411: 1 original) (Box 348 and 411, Video-cassette ME087)
    Producer: WGBH
    Original Credits: Producer and Director: Greg Barker
    Documentary on the survival of the Iraqi dictator Saddam Hussein, includes interviews with Said Abureish, Ahmed Chalabi, and other Iraqi opposition group members. Documents the history of Saddam's rise to power and his ability to survive crises in his rule, including the Gulf War, the post-war uprisings and sanctions against his regime.
    When the Gulf War ended, the United States government believed the Iraqis would quickly overthrow Saddam Hussein. But nine years later, he still rules Iraq. Frontline investigates Saddam's ruthless rise to power and how he has maintained his grip despite pressure from economic sanctions, no-fly zones, UN weapons inspectors, and military attacks from the Iraqi opposition.
  - UNHCR-Afghans Fleeing Fighting in Kabul, PAL VHS [TRT:0:10:20] (Box 349: 1 copy; Box 411: 1 original) (Box 349 and 411, Video-cassette ME088)
    Producer: Italian Production
    Contains footage of Afghan refugee camps and refugees who have fled the fighting in Kabul, includes women telling their stories in Pashtu. Includes footage of street scenes, money changers, near refugee camps. Interviews with United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees (UNHCR) workers describing the setups of the camps, the exact whereabouts which are unknown, unsure if they are in Kabul, probably outside of Kabul. Also, shows UNHCR relief trucks delivering food and water to the refugees as well as facilities for making bread and feeding the refugees. Also, shots of a red crescent medical station sponsored by the World Health Organization (WHO). Also descriptions of land mines and more very short interviews with refugees. Description of the closed Pakistan border, and footage of the border situation with Pakistani border guards preventing refugees from Afghanistan from entering Pakistan. Includes short interview with man who was able to cross. Also includes footage of Afghan refugees in the mountains.
  - CNN Perspectives: Revolutionary Journey [2000 Feb. 27], NTSC VHS [TRT:0:55:00] (Box 349: 2 copies; Box 413: 2 originals) (Box 349 and 413, Video-cassette ME089)
    Producer: CNN Perspectives
    Original Credits: Reporter: Christianne Amanpour
    Christianne Amanpour documentary about the situation in Iran, mixed in with her personal story of her family and their experience with the revolution and exile to the United States. "The only question now is how will the revolution end?" Includes mixture of old archival footage with footage of contemporary Iran. The story privileges the tales of Western oriented young people who would rather party and listen to rap music than participate in the Iranian revolution. Emphasis on the "desire" for these western, English speaking, upper class Iranians to lead a double life and participate in behavior illegal in the Iran of today. Includes photo and testimony of a man who was punished for participating in parties, describing this as a way of "resisting" the revolution, a "desire for freedom over fear". Also footage of the protests and riots on the campus of Tehran University during the summer of 1999, including women protesting. Hardline police beat and punished the students. Includes interviews with the organizers of the student protests. Also includes interviews with members of her family about her family history and support of the revolution. Also includes reports on the use of the internet in Iran and the desire for Western music and films, again on the part of the wealthy Iranian upper classes. Also interviews with college student, Fatemeh Haghighajou, who is religious and yet wants freedom in Iranian society and wants an interpretation of Islam based on reform movement of Iranian president Khatami. She is also elected to the new Iranian Parliament. Also an interview with Muvadi Savogi, one of the hardest of the hardliners in the Iranian government about the desire for reforms and freedoms. Includes reports on freedom of the press, which has since been repressed, Amanpour calls it the battleground of ideas. "Democracy is being born in these newspapers." Includes report on publisher Hamid Reza Jalalaipour. Shows the journalist to be deeply religious and yet against the regime.
  - Genocide By Sanctions, NTSC VHS [TRT:0:25:00] (Box 348: 1 copy; Box 413: 1 original) (Box 348 and 413, Video-cassette ME090)
    Producer: International Action Center
    Original Credits: Produced and Edited by Gloria La Riva. Associate Producers: Brian Becker and Richard Becker
    Documentary showing details of the sanctions against Iraq by the American government and there effects on children, with images of suffering children in hospitals, and with testimonies of Iraqi doctors.
  - Iran Scola News Report-March 1993, NTSC VHS [TRT:3:30:00] (1 original) (Box 413, Video-cassette ME091)
    Iran Scola News Reports of Iranian television on numerous subjects: a speech by Ali Khamenei, Islamic rebels in Tajikistan, Somalia, conflict in Balkans, American/British negotiations on Northern Ireland, Cuba, sports, environmental issues in Iran, weather, OPEC news, Palestine, Afghanistan, meetings of President Rafsanjani with foreign leaders, various committee meetings, industry in Iran, Bosnia-Herzogovina, demonstrations in West Bank, conflict in Algeria, Iranian parliament, Iranian crafts industry, education, conflict in Afghanistan.
    Dated 1993 Mar. 14 and 1993 Mar. 7-9.
  - Kurdish Tape #1, PAL VHS [TRT:2:06:00] (Box 349: 2 copies; Box 413: 1 original) (Box 349 and 413, Video-cassette ME092)
    Language: Kurdish
    Original Credits: LR Tape #2
    One original tape divided into two Beta's and two viewing copies.
    Tape A: Interviews with mine victims, and victims of chemical attacks, including Halabja, inflicted by the Iraqi regime against the Kurds during the Anfal, showing injuries and evidence of injuries along with interviews of doctors and nurses. These interviews are done by an unidentified German journalist, with the interviews mainly in German, also shots of Suliemaniya prison where alleged torture took place, also introduced by German journalist.
    Tape B: Bad quality shots of Kurdish art exhibit, shots of digging up mass graves and statements by Kurdish survivors of Saddam's chemical weapons attacks, sheikh giving a sermon over the graves, interview with child prisoner Taymour, exhibiting his wounds.
  - Paying the Price: Killing the Children of Iraq [2000 March 6], NTSC VHS [TRT:1:27:00] (Box 349: 1 copy; Box 412: 1 original) (Box 349 and 412, Video-cassette ME093)
    Producer: Carlton Television Ltd.
    Original Credits: Correspondent: John Pilger. Written and Produced by John Pilger. Film and Archive Researcher: Ursula Riley. Researcher, Iraq: Felecity Arbuthnot. Produced and Directed by Alan Lowery
    A Special Report by John Pilger
    Documentary about the deadly effects of sanctions imposed by the United Nations on Iraq after the Gulf War, and the bankrupt nature of American and British foreign policy in this regard, including continued air attacks upon Iran. John Pilger reports from Iraq on the condemnation of Iraqi society by economic sanctions and the subsequent isolation, killing more people than the two atom bombs, and killing over 500,000 children. Interviews with Iraqi pediatrician, Dr. Jinan Ghalib Hassen, Professor Karol Sikora, Former Chief of Cancer Programme of the World Health Organization (WHO), Denis Halliday, Former Assistant Secretary General, UN, James Rubin, US State Department spokesman, Ambassador Peter van Walsum, Chairman, UN Sanctions Committee, Dr. Jawad Al-Ali, Cancer Specialist, Hans von Sponeck, Chief UN Coordinator, Iraq, Mohammed Amin Ezzet, conductor, Iraqi National Orchestra, Robert Gates, CIA Director 1991-93, Scott Ritter, UN Weapons Inspector, Said Abureish, Felecity Arbuthnot, Journalist, Hussain Jarsis, Shepard, Laith Kubba, Iraqi Opposition exile and speeches by Robin Cook, UK Foreign Secretary, and Madeline Albright.